I am going to hand over now
with our performances this evening.
to John and Maria and Mark
and I think is that,
and venerable groups and talented artists
whose names need no introduction.
yes, that's all of you for figures.
and venerable groups and talented artists
whose names need no introduction.
Hello everybody.
So thank you, Dina, for that
great presentation and combination.
So this piece is one
that I've been wanting to do for a while,
Or reviving a stillborn child behind
the scenes melodrama in three acts.
pretty much since I started teaching
AI in my graduate course,
and also thinking
about the future of scholarship
and creative work
as part of the MLA working Group.
So I invited my two longtime collaborators
who have gone on journeys
with me and other projects
to do a live performance of something
that is not prescriptive
but is in fact scripting live
in the tradition of live coding.
Thank you very much. And this work.
So I'm John Murray and my collaborators
And then I'm going to run a video
from my students who did the actual work.
can introduce themselves,
and then I'll give you a brief
about the piece
and then we'll dive into it.
So there you go.
In 1999,
Thank you John.
Hello everybody I'm Maria Cecilia.
I'm based in Colombia.
And as John mentioned,
we have been working in other,
even if had I retyped it by hand.
adventures, narrative adventures
and immersive adventures in the past.
And now we join forces to understand how.
So it was my dead
child for a very long time.
Authorship works
when co-creating not only with AI agents,
but also with other people
and also with the audience
in in a live performance.
So yeah, we are very excited about this
experiment that we are all part of.
the last three years recreating this work.
Hi. Yes.
And I'm, I'm Mark,
another one of the collaborators
from the Shields Down
days, and I am happy to be joining in.
And this, by the way,
that you're looking at the twine.
John said we get to play with some code
indirectly get to play with some bots,
get to see what happens with cooperation,
authorship and collaboration.
And but what I really want
is my downloads.
That's right up my alley.
So I'm very excited to see what happens.
And let's start.
All right, so
everyone here may be familiar with P5, JS
it was one of the most popular languages
for the ILO Gallery.
This piece is a live, networked piece
where you all will be able
to log in to the app, which is up
for the duration of the performance.
leading to stone moons
being declared dead in 1999.
You all can hear.
In 2023, a team of Quin, Carrick, Genuine
and Me Claire
I got a request to make the code
a little bit bigger.
Is that better? Okay.
of the work in hopes of recreating
stone moons in a modern era.
This required scouring every single
one of the 477 nodes,
So this piece
let me copy this and share it in.
and the thousands of links
which connected them.
You all are now
welcome to join as audience members
and I'll post the link in the chat.
The blue nodes that make up the perimeter
represent Sara, and the glass rim.
Entering the rim lets
you delve into the heart of the work
So this is a live
updated p5 js
I can make changes to the background
and then hit run
and it will make those changes directly.
to life was quite a challenge as the work
was not only partially functioning,
And in this way, you know, as
an author you can track the changes over
time, much like you would with GitHub.
And this is something we have tracked
authorship that maybe someone enters
in a line of code and therefore
they authored that line of code.
That change is something
that they inscribed with their intention.
Now when you bring in collaborators
like I have, we have these discussions
about what the behavior should be,
why it should do it.
And these are also authorship acts,
but they're not acts
that directly touch the code.
So we've thought a little bit about
how do you represent
some of these different levels
of authorship of a piece,
and at what point do we start
acknowledging that
the authorship isn't always human,
especially as we invite another?
So I'm going to invite in the additional
the text was copied into our spreadsheet
and had all linked content bolded.
When moving on to a new node,
performers who are
my two agents that are going to join,
and they're going to take a small role,
much as they have
in many people's practices,
to help with writing code
and making changes.
on this layer, we would generally decide
to move to the next node based off of left
Oh, and those two people aren't us, John.
You're saying
those two people aren't us? No.
Those are not people at all.
They are, in fact, agents.
After transcribing a1, b1 and observing
zero nested nodes, we would
So once they join,
let's see if they'll pop in here.
See, this pattern would eventually lead us
to node a1, B2C to d1, e1,
Okay, so we've got Codex
and we've got Claude here.
In a moment, we can ask them
to perform actions on our behalf,
just like we would in cloud code.
So go ahead,
guys, and begin interact with them.
They can't hear what we're saying.
They can only see what we chat
through the text.
So we are inscribing our intentions
through the text in this shared chat
with them and each other as we wait.
John, now
you're now you're talking to us, right?
They and me. Yes. That's right. Okay.
You're telling us to join it? Okay, great.
Yes. No.
You should type in commands
and or interactions
through the chat inside of the interface.
spreadsheet,
I began prepping a twine file to
So for instance,
right now we have this very visual piece.
I could add text in there.
Or I could ask the agents to perhaps
do some textual interactions.
dimensional canvas was a problem
I needed to solve.
And I had some text and I see
Mark already added it.
being placed along their parents
angle from the center.
After placing Laurel's world
in the center of the canvas,
we had a representation of story spaces
three dimensionality inside of twins
2D canvas.
So at this point
a lot of us who have worked with AI,
While we had solved one problem
with integrating the work intertwined,
Quinn will tell you how we solved other
problems that came about while working
we understand that you
you write English language text
and the agent interprets it
and then inscribe that into the code.
So this this interface emulates
that by having the agents observe the chat
and then make changes to it.
The first issue was performance.
Entwine. Harlow.
The standard way to create
a link is a simple markup syntax
text in brackets
pointing to a destination.
But it's something
where they seem to be testing.
Hey Guy, you can also go back to previous
edits here in the revision history.
So this was the initial sketch.
Here's the one that I did.
We could add comments if we wanted to
and we could restore these things.
So I'm going to dismiss this.
We're talking unusable slow.
So I switched entirely to Harlow's link.
Okay.
We've got authority figure. So
Go to macro, which gave the reader
the exact same experience,
line one.
Line two.
They added the title to the piece.
I kind of like something like The Matrix.
So maybe some text falling from the sky.
Clicking
a highlighted word could bring up a menu
Man, we have the same great idea
saying a like.
of possible destinations, each
with its own named link.
So wait, was that your idea or my idea?
How do we how do we tell his idea?
I know it got it.
I think it was the bots.
Dena used them to tell jokes at
irony and layer meaning on top of meaning.
Why are they doing
brace tests in the chat?
Twine doesn't have anything like that
natively.
Every twine link goes to exactly
one place.
Our first attempt was a CSS hover
dropdown.
And then we've got the audience
down at the bottom.
So right now the agents can't
actually see the audience members chat,
but you can see each other's chat
in the peanut gallery down there.
So you all are in fact,
joining the performance.
The dropdown would cover parts of the page
and on nodes with multiple links.
All right.
So it's making some changes.
The changes seem to be valid.
We've got some following things that looks
more like asteroids than it is.
After weeks of research,
I found modal window
The text that we were looking for.
code for Twine Harlow
that I knew I could adapt.
The system works
through two dedicated notes.
A header node sits
invisibly on every page, and a modal code
That was my fault.
I asked them to bring some ashes
falling down the screen.
node contains the actual window
and its inline CSS.
Oh no. No faults.
There's no no apologizing
in this wacky collaboration.
the window appears and it's populated
with whatever link go to.
Okay, so you notice each of these changes
have a little commit
log to them so we could see each of these
individual versions by clicking on them.
And everyone in the audience
should be able to navigate
between the versions as well.
And then you just hit dismiss
to go to the latest version.
This exciting new code is available
if you open stone moons entwine.
With the functionality in place,
Jen will tell you how
she brought the visual side
of Stone moons back to life.
When stone moons moved from story
space to twine, something subtle
but important was lost.
We mostly asked them to do things.
They're basically performing actions
on our behalf.
Story space maps let you traverse the work
in a three dimensional way,
They're not really authors
in our traditional sense.
We certainly wouldn't label
an AI in the piece as an author, right?
Twine, by contrast,
shows one passage at a time.
Because who would be the coauthor?
Is it Claude in us,
or is it simply us asking
Claude to do something that we intend?
And this is something that I have
my students think about,
and it's something
which gets more and more complicated
the stronger the agents get.
space maps for Sarah's 16 major passages
And as you all know, agents,
with the introduction of fable
and the latest Codex models
certainly have gotten very capable
of producing interesting
creative, visual and textual works.
The moon's passages fill the interior,
and then I built a color
Okay, so now we've eliminated the previous
version in favor of a new version.
coded system to make the three voices
legible at a glance.
Sarah and blue laurel in yellow and green.
This one's inspired by the
dream life of letters.
The moon and red.
That color system
runs through every border shadow,
and in the piece is the visual grandma.
Oh, we got our House of dust thing
finally activated.
Readers learn without realizing it.
The interactive half of our named Ling
system belongs to Quinn.
He wrote the Harlow Macro code that fires
every time a reader clicks a navigation
So the agents can see
all of the other actions
and revisions and chat.
He wrote the Harlow Macro code that fires
every time a reader clicks a navigation
They're picking and choosing
and overwriting things.
But we're losing
some of the previous threads as well.
My contribution is to put a skin
on Quinn's code for the multi nodal links
appear CSS pop up, no JavaScript
that fades in with a half second opacity
transition, floats above the text
and is styled to feel like a story.
Space.
Dialog from 1999 couldn't handle the logic
I handled the surface.
This was my first original CSS
contribution to the project
from January 2025.
Underneath
everything is a design token system.
CSS custom properties
defined ones at root,
cascading across all 477
passages
from January to May 2025, the seasons
All right.
So you didn't put your flames yet?
grew from 1191 characters
to over 22,000 characters.
Well, there they are.
Speak of the devil.
There are nearly two megabytes
of fully self-contained twine, HTML,
no CDN, no external libraries, and the CSS
Oh, there we go.
Oh, and there's our smoke.
can be used for other projects
to show maps within twine.
The CSS is the skin of this project.
So everyone.
Dena gave me a shape to make it visible.
Can interact with it.
Once we do something a little bit
less passive and simply visualizing.
So P5 JS
is definitely a very interactive media.
So you might not see something exactly
the same as what's going on zoom
right now.
net. As
this work is near and dear to my heart,
And you can resize the font
and change it if you haven't logged
in on your own computer.
Vancouver and this amazing team
Claire Layton, Quinn Carrick
and Janine under Dean Gregoire
and the Electronic Literature Lab
cannot thank you enough.
Yay! And let's see here.
So I still am sharing my screen,
and I am told
Now can you
is it it's not interacting with our cursor
just yet.
that I have a few more minutes.
It is.
If you click on it, it'll shoot off
fireworks now.
Okay. Absolutely. Yes.
Oh, nice.
So first off,
a big shout out to my students.
I could not have done this without them.
And I want to tell a little story
real fast about this as well.
I did not want to look at this work.
And now when you move,
the mouse will push away the letters.
I refused to look at this work because
The mouse doesn't like the letters.
The letters are afraid of the mouse.
if I looked at this work,
I knew I would want to change it.
There I inscribed narrative
onto the Tetris blocks.
I remember what I was doing,
and so I did not look at the work.
And they kept telling me,
you know, Dina, this undercover work,
this link that's under coverings
doesn't work anymore.
This links that Selena's
dream doesn't work anymore.
And I'm like,
oh yeah, I wouldn't worry about it.
Whatever. Does it work?
Just put it as corrupted file
and we're going to show the work anyway.
And then they got it to me,
and I realized that
these two lovely little links
actually were the main navigation
structures of the whole thing. So.
I didn't
quite understand how the stuff worked.
And now I've got some comments
throughout here.
And so I used regular links
just because two I wanted to see how I did
this, and I needed to link
under coverings. And.
Celine's dreams to every text piece
Oh, yeah, I told you I had some things
for critical studies
people to do to get to interact with,
because this is the navigation. So.
although not that we just read comments.
That is why when you download
twine now, you will see that
there are actually links.
Dreamlike drifting alphabet letters
lean away from the cursor.
So it's not just, well,
it seems like it's jumping away
from the cursor.
Yes. So you see how
So what can you tell me about this code
mark?
Oh, you're gonna make me do on the
fly code studies, reading.
actually see the entire work.
Read the tea leaves.
Oh my goodness.
And here we go. Yes.
So you get to see the insides
of a very complex work.
Maybe I can get it to interpret itself.
So you get to see the insides
of a very complex work.
And here is Laurel's world.
Here is the main part of the work.
And the 16 nodes that start Sara's world.
And given all of that, I will also go
into the actual work and show
you real fast as we enter stone moons.
Others.
Janeway.
Janeway the chicken.
all of those links to our actual jokes.
And of course I had to rewrite these
because I don't remember
what the jokes were.
I remember that I had them,
I remember that
there was a navigational structure,
what they were, I don't know.
Oh, wow.
What is happening?
Did someone send it back to.
How's the dust? Or. It's just recursively.
I think they're starting
to make their own choices. Oh.
If Dire Straits robbed a grocery store,
they'd get their honey for nothing
We should.
Yeah.
There's
something like called autonomous move.
I don't know what it's going on here.
I don't think we actually.
Hold on.
How do we contain the agents?
We need to get them back on path.
Good idea.
What is the path?
Don't. Well, we're the path, right?
We're the authors.
We can't just let AI take over
the role of authorship.
who is the mother of Laurel,
Mark, I think you need some water.
who is an autistic child.
We need some water. Let's get some water.
Yeah, okay.
Let's get some water from the skies.
with the moon because the moon may,
may or may not want Laurel's soul,
the autistic child soul.
Oh, no.
And so in the Moon legends,
everything is a legend.
What's going to happen?
Hold on a second.
And I know that I had a navigational page
that became a legend.
So every one of these links
I actually don't like that mouse clicked,
causing the thing.
I want to delete it while I still can.
Is that navigation?
The other navigation
then comes with Laurel,
and Laurel does actually speak
through facilitated.
So. Well, clod is writing the script.
Communication.
You, as authors can control
some of the script or none of it.
And we talk about the
the facilitated communication here.
We can.
We can edit it,
but not as fast as the agents can.
And we have
the collection of
Let me move a few of these letters
from the alphabet soup
so they stop appearing.
So technically in a facilitated
typing exercise you take the child's hand
and you keep it above the keyboard.
Because after all,
if you look at our authorship meter,
I'm afraid the performer is only at 29.3%.
So we don't know
if Laurel actually wrote this.
And thus we have
What?
I'm not winning this battle, Mark pay.
And this becomes Laurel's world.
You know what I think?
in the very center of the piece,
I think they have to be able
to see what the audience says.
They can't just pay attention to us.
I vote we let the audience in.
Wait, we've got it.
We've got a new member in our in,
just so you know.
was to read through the work a little bit
and give you a bird's eye
Oh, oh, you're right, you're right.
So maybe you should deny that.
Don't don't say yes. Who do we have?
view of the code behind this, and of the
three years that it took to do this work.
We have we have Angley here
as the opps I believe.
So I'm going to stop
sharing now and hoping.
And I don't see my students here,
but that's okay.
We have a new performer.
This audio. This author joined too late.
Do they get the same credit as everyone
that was here before?
I just wanted to give them as much credit
as I possibly could for this
Well, yes.
Same wages
and deal with it.
I believe that's that's down. Right.
But they inherited
all of our creative decisions.
How can they possibly be freed to do
their own equal authorship of this work?
I see just checks and checking the chat,
but I will give my presentation
I mean, they're in charge
of sustaining this code, so good luck.
time up to John
and maybe we will have time to discuss it.
But thank you for letting us look
behind the scenes at Stone Moon's.
Since we don't know,
we don't even know what we've added.
The UPS is already giving
destructions.
I'm afraid the agents have started
taking on too much water.
It's it's
wonderful to see behind the scenes
Water?
We really need to control them. No point.
Good thing.
Let's bring in the entire audience,
okay, I approve, you all need to approve.
Every performer needs to approve.
Otherwise, you know
we all have to turn our keys together.
Yeah. Brilliant.
Oh, God. Okay, wait.
So where's what's the button?
Is it the top?
See where it says approve? Yeah.
Oh I see.
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Sorry. It's just like space team.
I'll just sleep at the wheel. Okay.
Approving the ops is,
I think, the only one remaining.
just because then we could get them
closer to the actual thing itself,
if that makes sense. But then keep them.
And then we could always come back to it
at the end.
Okay, so at this point, the
audience members can now talk to the bots
through the audience chat.
Okay, I'll allow it.
They will see the chats going there.
And God have mercy on all of our souls.
You have made a compelling case, John,
and I will allow it to proceed.
Talk about your space team.
So I make it.
So do it as Janeway would say.
Janeway the captain, not Janeway
the chicken.
Yes.
We have a whole Voyager crew,
so I'm trying to see
if there are questions in the chat
for Dina.
Exactly.
So if anyone has questions,
While this goes on.
I'm going to go through
a couple of these revision histories.
Assertive move the actual source lines
now goes behind the piece
per mark. Request that visuals
reflect the code frames as evidence
that credit is unstable.
I'm just glad
that we've sort of rescued this work
Move added unattributed murmurs
and a chicken named Janeway,
I think it's a really beautiful piece,
and it's one
whose own name Keith's glitching
authorship destabilized on purpose.
that you can dive into.
I don't know if I see the chicken
on the bottom believe it's there.
Oh, oh, you can't see it.
I can see it's
on the bottom of the screen.
It might be because I'm zoomed in.
Yeah,
that's why there's the chicken down here.
Oh, it's not a pelican
riding a bicycle, but it's not bad.
what this work was,
was one of my dearest friends in the world
who I had known since fifth grade,
And then we've got a few others.
So everybody you're welcome
to click on these different versions
that are in the revision history
and activate them to see the changes over
time.
the second worst case in Colorado.
And we were allowed to say
worst case in the 90s.
And we were working with this child
And here's the code itself
making its way into the piece.
And we were working with this child
Now come on. This is just too meta.
This is like a filmmaker
making a film about film.
we managed to get him to actually
Yes, exactly.
But we are going in different directions
while John is doing
all these layers of building this piece.
That gave social services
the impetus to take the child.
At the same time,
I am bringing in a very dark and on fire
and has custody, you get 5,000
USD a month from the federal government.
mode and smoky mode.
And Mark, yeah, he brought the chicken.
If the mother owns the child
and has custody, you got $1,000
I'm basically agent of Chaos.
Yeah.
So the state had a really good
financial incentive to take this child.
And we had been fighting all the time.
So everything
is just becoming more and more chaotic.
and another child
who was brilliantly gifted.
Did we ever get our water
that Stephanie asked for looking?
She in 1990, we managed the 1990s.
I think they ignored you. I think they
We managed to have a microphone system.
yeah, that feels familiar.
Her husband was amazing at this
and was in Antarctica,
Certainly
the lines of text
have to go in so rectilinear,
but and we she dictated her emails to me
and a few other people.
but it's a good point.
No, that's right,
they should not. Yeah, maybe.
Well, we could have them rain down again
if we wanted that for our water.
And I was advocating,
but at the same time, for both my friend
But we also have them in waves.
Okay. Let's, let's let's change that.
Hold on. I'm giving the command.
But Stephanie suggested it.
I don't know, I feel like I'm now
getting credit for someone else's idea.
And so having this work be a stillborn
work when it was going to be a political
This whole mechanical credit attribution
thing.
I think it's a wash.
Like, what did the agents do?
What did we do?
Give up the idea of credit
and and focus on what you want.
And we did manage to save some of it
in political manifestos.
But who's going to get the bonus
at the end of this performance?
Somebody for putting all that work in.
Don't we run out of credits?
nothing compared to what we lost in
Stone moons,
Oh yeah.
Good point.
Oh that's true I think I think the agents
are stealing all the fish.
and it was too hard
emotionally to take back.
Haven't
we been to use made tokens as we can?
Isn't this how this works?
and glad to take it on.
Yeah,
I think so.
All right.
Petra.
I think the agents are tired.
I don't see as many changes now.
It is
a work that spread out because we could
Okay, so
no sound, no water,
no waiting, waving lines of text.
I think you saw that
we could do those layers.
Stephanie,
now you know what it's like to be mean.
Nobody listens to your suggestions, ever.
the moon story with Sarah's and those go
You just.
You just calling off into the void.
I agree, I think I'm going to have to fire
the set of agents and hire a new set.
I have every time I talk about
this, I have to have a glass
I mean, they are just disposable cogs.
And I credit this
to Anastasia Salter in the chat.
Okay, fine, I will my screen again,
but the top of the rim is of the glass.
And yes, we can manually edit these
and remove things and edit things.
Is the intro into Sarah's world.
Now press yeah I'm going to get rid
of this mouse press thing for instance.
The 16 nodes that introduce
each chapter, each horrible event.
Yeah.
Now what
else are we going to make changes here too
And then we have on the side
Laurel's world
I think yeah the author is undefined
is pretty good.
and I'm sorry, Sarah's world, and Sarah
talking about those events.
And then inside the glass
we have the blood of the moon or wine.
And then the bottom of the class
is Laurel's world.
Oh that's a syntax error.
I'm going to break the entire piece.
There we go.
Oh, now our letters
are doing slightly different things.
I mean, I'd love to do this in VR.
I'd love to do this
navigational structure in VR.
No rain yet.
No, I think the agents have stopped.
I am picking them a little bit
behind the scenes now
to keep them going, but.
The reason for the wine glass
See, I'm not the one who speaking.
PD is that is the story.
The structure is the story.
The story is the structure.
Sarah's internal world is
both the legend of the moon
and the moon's blood.
Sarah is trying to protect her
Agents,
I need you to listen to me carefully.
I'm going to type this into your commands.
Just cease interacting with anything.
Your part here is done.
And so the rim of the glass is.
Is this really Laurel's words,
or is it a
is still an extension of the glass?
Is this still Sarah?
We don't know.
And that is not answered
in the story at all.
Agents, I command you.
So that's
where the image of the glass came from.
We are in their hands.
And yeah, and the stone
Well, I don't know.
I feel like humans. We've got some agency,
right? We're.
We're the resistance from the matrix.
We should be able to oppose AI together.
I think it's going to take all of us,
though.
We're going to have to edit the code.
We're going to have to do
all the work, not rely on AI.
But yeah, the three main
characters are Sarah, Laurel
Oh, no,
I can't even read this code.
It's a mess.
So thank you for the questions
I appreciate that.
Excellent. Thank you very much.
Oh, and I will put
I should put I forgot to do that.
Oh, I know why we can't get rain,
because we used up all the water
when we were making this piece.
Yeah.
Stick that in there. Yep.
I think it got a little confused
from all the audience input. Oh.
Okay.
As John noted, we can always
if you come up with questions,
I like some of the phrases, though,
that I can see behind
all the the ashes and the fire.
And we can come back to them
when both pieces are finished.
Are you reading the poetry?
Yeah.
Thank you. Dina, thank you so much.
I think
this is really valuable insight into
Do you want to read some of them today?
I think
this is really valuable insight into
where a work came from
and the different elements
A mouth Without a name
never signed the dark
where the name should be.
that went into it and the whys and hows,
and it's really important for
Your face dissolves before mirror ashes.
and it's really important to be able
to see how these things develop.
A mouth without a name.
Static.
Where a name should be.
What do you want to share?
The reading was.
You can both read some
please.
And remember no hand.
Who wrote this frame.
The Ashley members know hand
that a name should be.
Your face dissolves before the mirror
answers.
The author is no.
The author is undefined.
The wound in the words share no origin.
Here's the falling rain.
It is arrived at last. Oh,
it's cooling down the fire,
so we should probably put out the fire.
We need.
We need some ocean.
Some blue.
I think we have a syntax error
somewhere in here.
All agents have returned
at least a little bit.
But what are they going to do?
Wait, wait I love, I love now
I'm seeing stuff in the audience.
I feel like we also need to read.
For example, disease. I love you, egg.
I love you
like a thing that doesn't even know it.
Loves another thing.
And Petra's a ray of sunshine
blasting all the fish and Dean as paragon.
Pierogi
and chim.
Chicken.
Chicken, chicken.
Chicken is. No.
Whoa!
What is happening?
Yeah.
What's that?
A creature?
Never signed the dark.
Silence assembles its own signature.
This specter said the same, unattributed.
The author isn't all.
Whoa!
What just happened? What?
What did happen?
That to basis.
Wait.
But everything just disappeared.
All that work.
Hopefully it was backed up.
Wait.
Hopefully.
What what
what was it playing with us again?
But. Well, what are.
Maybe it was
in fact never here in the first place.
Maybe it was just a dream.
Oh, maybe code isn't permanent.
I think we need a trigger warning on this
for all of our programmers.
It's true.
This is too familiar.
I can't find the ocean.
I'm afraid it's not going to arrive.
They seem to do whatever they want now.
Yeah,
alright.
Yeah, I think,
I think with that I want to open the floor
for any further comments.
And yes, thinking about this is really
made me feel more in despair because
I haven't written a single line of code
throughout this entire performance.
But I think of myself as a programmer.
Well, I say good job, good job. But.
You're not very responsive
to our request spots.
They just abandoned abandoned performers.
Good good good good good job.
John and Mark.
Nice.
Thank you.
And there's one last little trick,
but I'll leave it for the Q&A.
Thanks, everybody.
Thank you.
With that, I'll happily address
some questions and discussions on this one
or even from the previous piece.
Thanks everybody, and feel free
to use these reactions at the bottom.
By the way, they'll just send
up little, you know, emojis.
Oh, thank you all very much.
I think that was either a very excellent
performance or I am very punchdrunk.
I think perhaps both.
I very much enjoyed that.
Gina is asking in the chat,
in all seriousness,
which I am incapable of at the moment.
I do like the Explore Dacian into who
and what is authorship, how do we archive
and who is the coder anyway?
Does this work? Spark. Spark?
I like it these age old questions.
Yeah,
because I mean, you write a line of code
and then who actually did it?
Is it you, the writer of the code?
The person that built the monitor?
Everyone's watching the code perform
its work on the writer
of the programing language, the developer
of the central processing unit,
and in the case of AI co-authorship,
the people that developed the AI models,
or the people whose work went into the
AI models either consenting or not.
I mean, this is something
I've been struggling with myself as I work
with AI and under about authorship
building data centers and.
Yeah,
I mean, like
right now we're facing this huge dichotomy
where there's a bunch of elites
that are going to profit off of AI
because of it being the modern
gold rush, the modern oil.
And then
they're creating these data centers
so that they can extract value out of it
and also sell it back to us in a way
that's very consumerism focused.
And how do we as a community respond
to that and not just simply accept it
and not simply reject it, but rather,
you know, critique it, engage with it,
play with it, hopefully get people
to think differently about it.
And of course, all of them,
because this is recorded.
So we have different ways
of archiving these things as well.
But it is an interesting idea
of what actually is the work.
Is it our responses to that work?
Is it your coding?
Who becomes the work?
And let me make sure I understand this.
What's going on is that you, as
players are providing prompts for Claude,
and Claude
is then doing the code,
and then that code is showing up, correct?
Yes. This is a play off of a multi-user
Claude that doesn't exist
unless you program it.
Right now, Claude's
model is very much one on one.
A user enters and prompts
to a command line interface for Claude
to then execute in the form
of creating source
files, editing things, making requests.
So so that's kind of how a lot of code
takes place right now.
But then, you know, is the prompts,
then the work is the work.
Simply the description
that then leads to the creation.
It's the same question as non-technical
contributors in a collaboration I think.
But why? What?
What is this drive to name
a singular author?
I mean, I don't understand that one.
And so there's an author in every single
work in the exhibition, isn't there?
Maybe.
Maybe not, maybe, maybe not.
So I'm saying it's it's a construct
whether or not it's true
and I'm poking at it.
It. Can Claude implement
sound if requested?
Yes, it can, but it did not.
I don't think anyone really asked for it,
but it can.
It can introduce like synthetic sounds.
It could, even
if it had access to it, create voices.
In fact, Claude was helping me
create the synthetic voices
that were the performances in scruff.
Stay.
The other piece I have in the
in the gallery with Anastasia Salter.
So yes, it can create
sound effects and voices and everything.
But going back to the
question,
this isn't just going to be a problem
or question
when it's an AI human interaction.
Like Stephanie saying,
when do you know who the author is?
Going back to my stone moons,
my best friend emailed me every day.
I took those emails
and I put them into two different buckets.
Yes, we're going to be in reality
and talking to the schools about this, but
we're going to be in fantasy
and go into stone moons and complain.
Am I the author?
No, because my friend wrote the emails.
But how much was that me writing?
How much was that her writing?
What happened?
And so I think that
this is a really good way of obscuring
who the author is,
but I think that happens no matter what.
To me, the author
is something that happened
a few hundred years ago.
Before that, it didn't happen.
Went, you know,
who was the author of the Iliad?
There's no Homer, you know what I mean?
There's like.
And when everything is
has so many collective
cultural resources that undermine
any piece of writing of any kind,
that I think this whole thing
of focusing down on the author
is it's a very commercial idea,
you know what I mean?
And I don't know why we should
buy into it.
It's not that these
things are making money or anything.
What I'm saying,
well, in some cases, if you do something
completely with AI right now,
you can't really copyright it,
but you could make money off of it.
So if you used AI to create a
game and then sold the game.
And I
could make money off of printing stuff off
on a Xerox machine,
which people used to do with the,
you know, scenes and so on like that.
But the focus wasn't on,
oh, this is the name of the author.
It could be many.
I mean, it could be multi-author.
It it could be.
I just think there was never a time
when you could securely say,
this is the author,
and think that you were tracking
every piece of input into the writing.
I actually agree with you quite a bit.
That's part of why I created this piece.
Now there is a little interruption
happening in the interface,
if you might have noticed.
So during the performance
I was actually doing
some programing in cloud directly to
control the interface running on there
and everything else.
So there was a man behind the curtain,
as it were.
Being overly dramatic about it.
But that's cloud for you.
All right.
I hope this was thought provoking. Yeah.
Brian has a has a nice comment.
Brian, you want to say that one aloud?
You want me to read it?
Yeah, please read it I was
I was can you hear me.
Yeah yeah yeah I was trying to be
a lurker, but anyway,
I'll just read what I wrote
and I, you know, I actually said this
in, I think one of my early essays
like privileged Privileging language,
my own problem with interactive text
works like this is that the text is almost
always pretty innocuous
and kind of describes
the experience, rather than runs as a,
as a kind of counterpoint
or tension against the experience.
That's why I use
that Dodie Bellamy text for Dream Life.
I got to use words like taunt, which I
which is not something I wrote myself.
And I don't say it very often.
No, I really don't.
Words like that were pulses or beats
in an experience that was otherwise
all green.
But of course, in realism
the dream was never without it.
And I meant that that that I just meant,
you know, dreams were pretty sexually
and fluid infused.
Not to mention having, you know, the other
apparatus ism.
Take it as you will.
I just I always felt like,
you know, these are really beautiful.
I mean, this is great.
I really love the fact that there was
a sense of process, and I'm assuming that
that that whole ending
where it just turned it into a swirling
series of
orbiting things was purposive.
Right?
I mean, you've made
it sound like it was an error, but
but really, that was the kind of payoff of
much, much was what was going on.
I assumed that way.
So that was my comment.
I love you know,
I didn't follow this all very closely,
but it looks like what the basic idea was
that you were doing a lot of wide coding
as you were presenting the work,
or does that make sense?
I mean, that's
the essence of the performance.
I guess you could say
the performance was critiquing.
Five coding is authorship
and its limitations compared
to traditional coding.
Although or maybe for me and Mark,
maybe it was by prompting
more than by coding.
Yeah, maybe a little human machine
collaboration.
Challenging questions as well.
You know, the push and pull between the
the people and the
and the systems.
But who's to say, I don't know
who's to say what this whole thing means?
A future ELO presentation, actually,
one of my inspirations was Jacob Garvey,
a a fellow grad student
from UC Santa Cruz, as his MFA thesis.
He did this show where he basically had
the A's escape during the performance
as part of the performance,
after having everybody,
you know, babysit their own eyes
and make it all sort of contained,
I thought he was really foresight,
looking at the future of AI
and human relationships, as it were.
Whereas right now
we have a very utilitarian approach them,
which is right now
embodied by vibe coding.
And as you get further along
in the strength and power of AI models,
it's less and less simply instructing
the model what you want it to do, and more
that the model does things that perhaps
the audience,
the member creating things through it
didn't want to have happen,
or maybe didn't even dream of happening.
And so they start to wonder if that's
something they did or something they did.
Got a question of
how does it feel to your three
when you play without any agents?
You might want to expand
a little bit on that, but otherwise
I think we've gone far too late.
This one has gone much longer
than the other performance.
Thanks, everybody.